Preliminary Inventory of the Richard P. Nathan papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Richard P. Nathan papers
1957-1979
80025
Nathan, Richard P.
67 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (27.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection relates to American politics and intergovernmental relations and to domestic policy, particularly welfare and revenue sharing programs, during the presidency of Richard M. Nixon. It contains correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, printed matter, and photographs.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
John Ehrlichman papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Forrest David Matthews speeches, Hoover Institution Archives
John G. Veneman papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
1935 Born
1957 Bachelors degree, Brown University
1959 Masters degree in Public Administration, Harvard University
1959-1962 Legislative assistant, U.S. Senator Kenneth B. Keating
1962-1964 Director, Domestic Policy Research, National Campaign Staff, Nelson A. Rockefeller
1966 Doctorate of Philosophy, Political Economy and Government, Harvard University
1967 Associate Director for Program Research, National Commission on Civil Disorders (Kerner Commission)
1968 Director, Domestic Policy Research, National Campaign Staff, Nelson A. Rockefeller
1969 Chair, Nixon Transition Task Force on Intergovernmental Relations Chair, Nixon Transition Task Force on the Poor
1969-1970 Chair, Domestic Council Committee on Welfare Reform Planning
1969-1972 Assistant Director, U.S. Office of Management and Budget
1972 Deputy Under Secretary for Welfare Reform, U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare
1972-1977 Visiting professor, Woodrow Wilson Department of Government, University of Virginia
1972-1979 Senior fellow, The Brookings Institution
1975 Author, The Plot that Failed: Nixon and the Administrative Presidency Author, Monitoring Revenue Sharing, with Allen D. Marvel and others, The Brookings Institution
1977 Author, Revenue Sharing: The Second Round, with Charles F. Adams, Jr., and Associates, The Brookings Institution
1979-1989 Professor of Public and International Affairs and Policy, Woodrow Wilson School, Princeton University
1983 Author, The Administrative Presidency
1987 Author, Reagan and the States, with Fred C. Doolittle and others
1988 Author, Social Science in Government, Uses and Abuses
1989-2004 Director, The Nelson A. Rockefeller Institute of Government, State University of New York
1989-2009 Distinguished Professor of Political Science and Public Policy, Rockefeller College, University at Albany, State University of New York
1993 Author, Turning Promises into Performance
1997-2001 Advisor, U.S. Government Accountability Office
2003-2004 President, Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management
2003-Present Member, New York State Commission on Judicial Nominations
2005-2009 Co-Director, The Nelson A. Rockefeller Institute of Government, State University of New York
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection relates to American politics and intergovernmental relations and to domestic policy, particularly welfare and revenue sharing programs, during the presidency of Richard M. Nixon. It contains correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, printed matter, and photographs.
As director of domestic policy research for Nelson A. Rockefeller's 1968 presidential campaign, Nathan kept organized binders of studies on domestic issues such as crime, youth, and poverty. These materials are included in the collection along with press releases and speeches from the campaign.
Reports and correspondence from Nathan's time as assistant director of the Office of Management and Budget detail the development of the Nixon administration's welfare reform proposals, including the Family Assistance Plan, from 1968 to 1972. Among these materials are studies relating to government assistance programs in New York and California, as well as background information packets compiled for Nixon's meeting with Governors Rockefeller and Reagan in 1971.
Other materials in the collection include memoranda received and studies administered by Nathan during his time in the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, drafts and proof copies of articles, editorials, and books written by Nathan, and research materials and writings on revenue sharing compiled while working as a fellow with the Brookings Institution.
The collection is arranged in the order in which it was received, with no further arrangement done by archives staff.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; United States. Dept. of Health, Education and Welfare.; United States. Office of Management and Budget.; Intergovernmental fiscal relations--United States.; Public welfare--United States.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.; United States--Social policy.
Collection Contents
- Writings on "New Federalism,", 1969-1972 (Folder 1)
- Rockefeller campaign. Public statements, 1968-1970 (Folder 1)
- Brookings Institution. Reports and writings, 1968-1970 (Folder 1)
- Office of Management and Budget background materials, 1970 (Folder 1)
- United States. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (HEW) files, 1971 (Folder 1)
- Goodell-Laind bill materials, 1966-1967 (Folder 1)
- Brookings Institution. Transcripts of conference proceedings, 1978 (Folder 2)
- Writings on welfare reform, 1972 (Folder 2)
- Clippings, 1972 (Folder 2)
- Books of Nixon campaign speeches and statements, 1968 (Folder 3)
- Brookings Institution. Reports, 1978 (Folder 3)
- Photocopies of clippings, 1972 (Folder 3)
- Memoranda, 1972 (Folder 3)
- Brookings Institution files (Folder 4)
- HEW file. Reports on health policy, 1970 (Folder 4)
- Printed matter and clippings on welfare reform (Folder 4)
- Drafts and research materials, 1965 (Folder 4)
- Rockefeller campaign. "Domestic Research,", 1968 (Folder 5)
- Rockefeller campaign. Report for Republican Governor's Association Policy Committee, 1967 (Folder 5)
- Memoranda, 1968 (Folder 5)
- Speeches and writings, 1971 (Folder 6)
- Brookings Institution. Reports, 1978 (Folder 6)
- Partial draft of The Plot That Failed (Folder 6)
- HEW file. Speeches, 1969-1970 (Folder 7)
- HEW file. Task Force on Welfare reports and office files, 1968-1970 (Folder 7)
- Rockefeller campaign. "Domestic Research,", 1968 (Folder 7)
- Office of Management and Budget. Reports, undated (Folder 7)
- Rockefeller campaign. Speeches and statements, 1968 (Folder 8)
- Rockefeller campaign. "Domestic Research,", 1968 (Folder 8)
- Heller-Pechmann plan (Folder 8)
- Brookings Institution files (Folder 8)
- Writings, 1960 (Folder 9)
- Statements by Kenneth B. Keating, 1961-1964 (Folder 9)
- HEW file. Family Assistance Act, 1970 (Folder 9)
- Public Welfare Association materials, 1972 (Folder 9)
- HEW file. Excerpts and statements, 1972 (Folder 10)
- State statistics for Colorado, 1972 (Folder 10)
- Drafts and working files, 1968-1969 (Folder 11)
- Intergovernmental Task Force materials (Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous writings and congressional acts, undated (Folder 11)
- Drafts, 1972 (Folder 12)
- Internal Advisory Committee reports (Folder 12)
- Intergovernmental relations, 1969 (Folder 12)
- Memoranda, 1969 (Folder 12)
- Drafts of articles and reports, 1970s (Folder 13)
- Public affairs file (Folder 13)
- Photographs of Nathan (Folder 13)
- HEW file. Studies and reports, 1969-1972 (Folder 14)
- Drafts, 1972 (Folder 15)
- HEW file. Health services and welfare reform reports, 1971-1972 (Folder 15)
- Research materials. International income security programs, 1970s (Folder 15)
- Commission on Income Maintenance Program (Folder 16)
- Government reports, 1970 (Folder 16)
- HEW file. Memoranda and correspondence re welfare, 1972 (Folder 16)
- Rockefeller campaign. "Domestic Research" and summary on positions, 1968 (Folder 17)
- Writings and memoranda relating to H.R. 1 and welfare reform, 1971-1972 (Folder 17)
- Clippings, correspondence and research materials, 1971-1972 (Folder 17)
- Writings, 1971 (Folder 18)
- Drafts of "Welfare Reform Under the Nixon Administration,", undated (Folder 18)
- Drafts of "Federalism and Tax Sharing,", 1967 (Folder 18)
- Rockefeller campaign. "Domestic Research,", 1968 (Folder 19)
- Sociology thesis, 1957 (Folder 19)
- HEW file. Reports, 1971 (Folder 19)
- Drafts, 1973 (Folder 19)
- Rockefeller campaign. "Domestic Research,", 1968 (Folder 20)
- Rockefeller campaign. "Domestic Research,", 1968 (Folder 21)
- Drafts of The Plot That Failed, 1973 (Folder 22)
- Rockefeller campaign. "Domestic Research,", 1968 (Folder 22)
- Writings on incidence analysis, 1973-1974 (Folder 23)
- Drafts, 1973-1974 (Folder 24)
- Rockefeller campaign materials, 1968 (Folder 24)
- Brookings Institution. Drafts of Monitoring Revenue Sharing, 1974 (Folder 25)
- Brookings Institution file, 1972 (Folder 26)
- Nixon transition team materials, probably 1969 (Folder 26)
- Miscellaneous papers relating to Keating, 1964, and Rockefeller, 1968 (Folder 26)
- Speeches, 1973 (Folder 26)
- Bureau of Budget (Office of Management and Budget) file. Statements and writings, 1974-1975 (Folder 27)
- Brookings Institution. Research materials, 1974-1975 (Folder 28)
- Correspondence, undated (Folder 28)
- Subject file. Revenue sharing, undated (Folder 28)
- Research materials, 1975 (Folder 29)
  Includes photocopies of clippings and notes
- Brookings Institution. Reports and newsletters on revenue sharing, 1975 (Folder 30)
- Drafts, 1971 (Folder 31)
- Published articles, 1970s (Folder 31)
- Transition data, 1968 (Folder 31)
- Intergovernmental Task Force reports, 1968 (Folder 32)
- Department briefings and reports (Folder 32)
- Subject file. Civil rights, undated (Folder 32)
- Brookings Institution files, 1976 (Folder 32)
- HEW file, 1972 (Folder 33)
- Articles and reports, 1976 (Folder 34)
- Government department reports and studies, 1968-1971 (Folder 34)
- Bureau of Budget file (Folder 34)
- HEW file, undated (Folder 34)
- Research materials, 1971-1973 (Folder 35)
- Keating campaign materials, 1964 (Folder 35)
- Correspondence, undated (Folder 35)
- Speeches and writings, 1975-1976 (Folder 36)
- "New Federalism" notes and research materials, 1973-1974 (Folder 36)
- Drafts and edits, 1974-1975 (Folder 37)
- Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Folder 37)
- Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Folder 37)
- Speeches, 1975-1977 (Folder 38)
- Correspondence, 1968 (Folder 39)
- Appendix of United States Government Budget for Fiscal Year 1972 (Folder 39)
- Brookings Institution. Revenue sharing, 1976 (Folder 40)
- Drafts of book chapters, 1974 (Folder 40)
- Voting record of Kenneth B. Keating (Folder 41)
- Writings on revenue sharing, 1975 (Folder 41)
- Reports to U.S. congress, 1975 (Folder 41)
- Questionnaires, 1974 (Folder 41)
- Drafts of book chapters, 1975 (Folder 42)
- Task Force meeting materials, 1975 (Folder 43)
- Subject file. Civil rights, 1975 (Folder 43)
- Testimonies, 1976 (Folder 44)
- Brookings Institution. Research report on revenue sharing, 1974 (Folder 44)
- Materials from meetings, 1975 (Folder 44)
- Office of Management and Budget programs, 1971 (Folder 45)
- Correspondence, 1975-1978 (Folder 45)
- Drafts of writings, 1974 (Folder 45)
- Keating campaign. Press releases, 1964 (Folder 46)
- Research materials for book, 1972 (Folder 46)
- Rockefeller campaign. Press releases, 1965 (Folder 47)
- Drafts of writings, 1964 (Folder 47)
- Keating files, 1964 (Folder 47)
- Two audio cassette tapes labeled "Task Forces Part 1" and "B.O.B. and The Plot That Failed Part 2,", undated (Folder 48)
- Keating files, 1963 (Folder 48)
- Materials from speaking engagements and correspondence, 1973-1974 (Folder 49)
- Speeches and writings, 1973-1974 (Folder 50)
- Speeches and writings, 1974 (Folder 51)
- Drafts of Monitoring Revenue Sharing, 1974 (Folder 52)
- Conference materials and speaking engagements, 1975-1976 (Folder 53)
- HEW file. Task Force on Man Power Coordination, 1972 (Folder 54)
- Chronological file, 1970-1971 (Folder 55)
  Includes correspondence, memoranda, and writings
- Chronological file, 1969 and 1972 (Folder 56)
- Excerpts from writings (Folder 57)
- Revenue sharing proposal, 1969 (Folder 57)
- Brookings Institution. Memoranda, 1967-1968 (Folder 58)
- Chronological file, 1966 (Folder 58)
- Research studies and clippings, 1968-1974 (Folder 58)
- Subject file. H.R. 1, 1970-1971 (Folder 59)
- HEW file. Welfare reform in California, West Virginia, and New York, 1972 (Folder 59)
- Photocopies of clippings, 1972 (Folder 59)
- Family assistance programs, 1968-1970 (Folder 60)
- Studies, data analysis, and reports, 1969-1971 (Folder 60)
- Memoranda, background materials, and notes from meeting with Rockefeller and Reagan, 1971 (Folder 60)
- Reports on Medicaid and welfare reform, 1969-1972 (Folder 61)
- Memoranda, background materials, and notes from meeting with Rockefeller and Reagan, 1971 (Folder 61)
- Binder. Budget and management transition data, 1968 (Folder 62)
- Miscellaneous, 1971 (Folder 63)
- Awards and framed photographs, 1970-1978 (Folder 64)
- Committee for Economic Development, Maine, 1965 (Folder 65: 1-4)
- Committee for Economic Development, Mississippi, 1965 (Folder 65: 5-8)
- Committee for Economic Development, Georgia, 1968 (Folder 66: 1-2)
- National Advisory Committee on Civil Disorders, short-term programs, 1967 (Folder 66: 3-7)
- Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Folder 67)
- Materials from speaking engagements, 1975 (Folder 67)
- Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Folder 68)
- Fiscal assistance programs, 1975 (Folder 68)
- Conference materials, reports, and studies, 1975-1976 (Folder 68)